Guide to the Joni Rabinowitz Papers, 1957-2008 AIS.2010.05
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Literature, 1966-1990; V.
  - The Realist Presents: The Last Supplement, March, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - RECON, Vol. 1 No. 7, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - The Red Papers, No. 2-3, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Resist, January, April and June, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Roadblock to Revolution: A Radical Critique of the Progressive Labor Party, By: Edward Greer and Charles Lengram, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Self Reliance, No. 10, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Sex Roles and Female Oppression By: Dana Densmore, undated (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Socialist Feminism: A Strategy for the Women's Movement, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Socialist Platform, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - South of the River, Vol. 1 No. 6, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - The Stages of Economic Stagnation By: John H. Coatsworth, undated (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - Studies on the Left, No. 1 Vol. 3, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - The Subversion of Collective Bargaining By: Daniel Bell, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 64)
  - To Build a Union By: Harry Anderson, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 65)
  - Toward a Female Liberation Movement By: Beverly Jones and Judith Brown, undated (Box 8, Folder 66)
  - Tricontinental No. 16, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 67)
  - United Labor Action, Vol. 4 No. 4, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 68)
  - The United Express, Vol. 1 No. 4, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 69)
  - US Imperialism By: David Gilbert and David Loud, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 70)
  - The Utah Coordinator, Vol. 1 No. 3 and Vol. 2 No. 4-5, 1967-1968 (Box 8, Folder 71)
  - Who Rules Somerville, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - Why We Strike, undated (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - The Wisconsin Patriot, Vol. 6 No. 4, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - Women: A Journal of Liberation, Vol. 1 No. 4, Vol 2 No. 3-4 and Vol. 3 No. 1, 1970-1972 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Womankind, Vol. 3 No. 3, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Women Organizing, No.9, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Women Workers: Some Basic Statistics By: Lisa Vogel, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - The Working People's Voice, Vol.1 No. 2B, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Working Women's Resource and Buying Guide to Greater Pittsburgh, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Yellow Fever, A Newsletter Written by Pittsburgh Cab Drivers, undated (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Young Minds Die Easy: A Case for Community Control, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Oversize Literature, 1970-1976
    This specific section consists of the oversize journals, GROK and the Pittsburgh Fair Witness, as well as the Pittsburgh and Wisconsin People's History Calendars. The materials are organized alphabetically. GROK started publication in the 1970s, publishing nine monthly issues before the title was changed to the Pittsburgh Fair Witness. Rabinowitz wrote for and distributed the Pittsburgh Fair Witness. The following editorial published in 1972 provides the papers statement of purpose:
    "The Fair Witness is published by a non-profit collective and is dedicated to the worldwide movement of people to control themselves—the movement to break down the authoritarian systems of government that are denying us our basic freedoms, that are responsible for needless genocidal wars, the perpetration of minority discrimination, the pollution of our environment and our bodies, the high concentration of power among the wealthy classes, exploitation of the individual, etc. The paper is dedicated to the struggle of all peoples to gain back the right to their own lives, the struggle to raise the consciousness of the world as a whole, the struggle to become independently productive through a working knowledge of the tools at our disposal. As a local paper our most important function concerns the movement here in western Pennsylvania."
    Rabinowitz helped create the Pittsburgh People's History Calendar which was produced by NAM's People's History Project. Records concerning the creation of the calendar can be found in the NAM series and "projects" subseries.
    - GROK Vol. 1 No. 3-9 (missing No. 7), 1970 (Oversize 9, Folder 1)
    - The Pittsburgh Fair Witness Vol. 1 No. 10-11, 1970 (Oversize 9, Folder 2)
    - The Pittsburgh Fair Witness Vol. 2 No. 1-7 (missing No.2), 1971 (Oversize 9, Folder 3)
    - The Pittsburgh Fair Witness Vol. 2 No. 10-14, 1971-1972 (Oversize 9, Folder 4)
    - The Pittsburgh Fair Witness Vol. 3 No. 2-8 (missing No. 7), 1972 (Oversize 9, Folder 5)
    - The Pittsburgh Fair Witness Vol. 3 No. 11-16, 1972 (Oversize 9, Folder 6)
    - The Pittsburgh Fair Witness Vol. 3 No. 17-20 and Vol. 4 No. 4-5, 1972-1973 (Oversize 9, Folder 7)
    - Pittsburgh People's History Calendar, 1975 (Oversize 9, Folder 8)
    - Wisconsin People's History Calendar, 1976 (Oversize 9, Folder 9)
- Personal, 1961-2004; VI.
  This series contains materials that document Rabinowitz's experiences during college and after in New York City, non NAM and DSA affiliated conferences and events, legal cases she was involved in, writings and correspondence, various projects, and involvement in other various organizations. This series is divided into six subseries in which folders are organized alphabetically, excluding "legal cases" which is organized chronologically.
  - College and New York City, 1957-1969; 1.
    This subseries documents some of Rabinowitz's activism while at college and after college when she moved back to New York City. Included are writings, events, scrapbook and other materials which are organized alphabetically.
    - Antioch College Student Organizations, Actions, and Publications, 1961-1963 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Anti-Poverty Teach In, 1965-1967 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Committee For Independent Political Action, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Helsinki Youth Festival, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Movement for a Democratic Society, 1968-1969 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Movement for a Democratic Society, Literature, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Movement for a Democratic Society, Welfare, 1968-1969 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - The National Committee to Abolish the House Un-American Activities Committee, 1961-1966 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Social Welfare Worker's Movement, 1964-1969 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), 1963-1964 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Political Activism and Activities Newsclipping Scrapbook, 1957-1963 (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
      This item is a scrapbook of newspaper articles spanning from 1957 to 1963. Most are from 1962 and 1963. The articles included in it relate to political events Rabinowitz was involved with or interested in during her college years. Most of the articles are about civil rights struggles, especially in Georgia, where Rabinowitz worked with the SNCC in 1963. Other topics such as the March on Washington and Cuba and the students who broke the travel ban to visit are included in the clippings. Many of the articles mention Rabinowitz for her involvement in civil rights demonstrations and her arrests. There are also a few articles that she wrote about her experiences. Box 12 also includes a folder of copies of the scrapbook.
  - Conferences and Events, 1966-1999; 2.
    Rabinowitz was not only active in attending various conferences and events through NAM and DSA, but her activism and involvement extended beyond and after these organizations. This subseries documents the various conferences and events she attended and is organized alphabetically.
    - Alternative State and Local Policies Conference, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Anti-Communism and the US: An International Conference, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Campus Organizing Action Conference, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Citizen's Action Midwest Academy Retreat, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Counter Bicentennial Demonstration, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Health Care for All Speaker's Seminar, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Morningside March, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Second Festival of the Revolution, Granada, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Strike City Benefit, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Women's Health Services 10th Anniversary Celebration, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Women of Achievement Recognition and Awards, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Various Conferences and Workshops, 1980-1984 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Legal Cases, 1964-1997; 3.
    This subseries documents the legal cases Rabinowitz was involved in and include legal documents, briefs, and newspaper clippings. Materials are organized in chronological order. Of interest are the The Gegner v. McKee and Rabinowitz v. The United States cases. Joni Rabinowitz v. The United States, or "Joni's Case" as it was known, involved she and five other members of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) who were indicted for perjury in 1963 when she testified that she was not present at a protest meeting in front of an Albany, Ga., grocery store. Her father, Victor Rabinowitz, defended her and won an appeal the next year. The Gegner v. McKee involved Rabinowitz and over one hundred Antioch College students and other civil rights activists who were arrested in 1964 after protesting against Lewis Gegner, a Yellow Springs barber who refused to serve African American patrons.
    - Albany By: Howard Zinn, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - The Albany Cases (pamphlet), 1962 (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - "Joni's Case", 1963-1965 (Box 10, Folder 25-26)
    - Joni Rabinowitz v. The United States, Brief of Amicus Curiae of American Scholars, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - Joni Rabinowitz v. The United States, Legal Briefs, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - Joni Rabinowitz v The United States Legal Briefs, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Gegner v. McKee Newspaper Clippings, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Gegner v. McKee Correspondence, 1964-1968 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Gegner v. McKee Legal Documents, 1964-1965 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Defiant Trespass, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Drug Bust, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Case Against Rabinowitz for the Distribution of Leaflets at the Monroeville Mall, 1996-1997 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Writings and Correspondence, 1964-2004; 4.
    This subseries is organized alphabetically and contains items written by Rabinowitz, which includes correspondence, academic papers, and newspaper editorials and pieces. Also included are items written about Rabinowitz which include newspaper articles, interviews, and academic papers.
    - Correspondence Regarding Breast Cancer Diagnosis, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence with Brother Concerning His Involvement in the Freedom Riders, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence with Martin Luther King Jr., 1964 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Letters to the Editors of Various Newspapers, 1973-1978 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Mastectomy Legislation, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Papers Written On Joni, 1989-1991 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1964-1988 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette Roundtable, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Press, 1964-2004 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Speeches, 1975-1980 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - University of Pittsburgh School of Social Work, 1972-1974 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Projects, 1973-1996; 5.
    This subseries contains materials pertaining to projects Rabinowitz was involved in, separate from the organizations she was a member of. Included are the advertising books that she created for different causes, evaluation and analysis of local organizations, an oral history project she became involved in, and papers that document her time at Wobblie Joe's Tavern as a manager. Materials are organized alphabetically.
    - Advertising Books, 1981-1982 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Celestial Seasonings Tea Distribution, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Evaluation and Analysis of Community Organizations in Pittsburgh, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Oral History Project, 1975-1996 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Resistance and Beyond: A Handbook Prepared by The Pittsburgh Resistance and Their Friends, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Wobbie Joe's Tavern, Manager, 1978-1981 (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Wobblie Joe's Tavern, Personal Notebook, 1978-1981 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Personal Involvement in Organizations, 1968-1996; 6.
    Included in this subseries are materials that document Rabinowitz's involvement in organizations throughout the 1970s, 1980s, and 1990s, separate from those related to the NAM or DSA. Materials are organized alphabetically.
    - Ad Hoc Committee to Counter Klan Activity, 1980-1981 (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - The Citizen's/Consumer Party Materials, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - Committee to Improve Kane Hospital, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 26)
    - Ejection from Democratic Platform Meeting, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - Fair Budget Coalition, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - The Gulf Action Project, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 29)
    - Jobs with Peace, 1981-1987 (Box 11, Folder 30)
    - Just Harvest Presentations and Testimonies, 1992-1996 (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - Heath Care for All, Post 1995 and Disbandment (Box 11, Folder 32)
    - Health Care for All, Canadian Tour, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 33)
    - Local 1199 in Pittsburgh, 1968-1970 (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - Relations with Congress of Afrikan People, Mass Party Organizing Committee, 1975-1976 (Box 11, Folder 35)
    - Relations with Socialist Worker's Party Campaign, 1973-1976 (Box 11, Folder 36)
    - Support Our Neighborhood Action Coalition, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 37)
    - Switchboard Community Telephone Service and Serve the People Coalition, 1970-1972 (Box 11, Folder 38)